A Guide to the Virginia Extension Homemakers Council Papers, 1948-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Virginia Extension Homemakers Council Papers, 1948-2007
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2011-090
14 cu. ft. 21 boxes
This collections includes institutional records, photographs, publications, yearbooks, slides, videos, and artifacts from the Virginia Extension Homemakers Council (currently named the Virginia Association for Family and Community Education). Materials in the collection date from 1948 to 2007.
National Extension Homemakers Council. Virginia Chapter. (U.S.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Virginia Extension Homemakers Council Papers were donated to Special Collections in 2011. Additional material was donated to Special Collections in 2013.
Historical Note
The Virginia Extension Homemakers Council (formerly the Virginia Home Demonstration Club and currently the Virginia Association for Family and Community Education) was founded in 1923 and was one of the founding members of the National Home Demonstration Council in 1936 (which changed its name to National Extension Homemakers Council in 1963 and later to National Association for Family and Community Education). These groups focus on programs that provide education on family and women's issues as well as provide opportunities for leadership development within the community. The organizations are affiliated with the Associated Country Women of the World.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes records, publications, yearbooks, slides, videos, and artifacts from the National and Virginia chapter of the Extension Homemakers Council (currently named the Virginia Association for Family and Community Education). Materials in the collection date from 1948 to 2007.
These records mostly pertain to the administrative and financial organization of the institutions but also encompass various programs and projects undertaken by the VEHC. There is a significant amount of information on the VECH Bicentennial tapestry project, both in written records and multimedia. Many of the slides pertain to 4-H club activities and camps. Artifacts in the collection consist of a 50th Anniversary commemorative plate and bell, 4-H award plaques, as well as the seal of the National Extension Homemakers Council and the Bedford 4-H crest and flag.
Arrangement
Series I: National Extension Homemakers Council includes materials relating to the national organization. Materials consist of newsletters, meeting minutes, administrative records, and memorabilia from Virginia meetings. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series II: Virginia Extension Homemakers Council consists of three subseries. Subseries A: Administration and Organizational History includes annual reports, meeting minutes, and membership materials. Subseries B: Programs and Projects consists of various programs like the Bicentennial Tapestry and local heritage projects that were undertaken by VEHC. Subseries C: Scrapbook and Memorabilia contains VEHC scrapbooks. All subseries are arranged chronologically.
Series III: Associated Country Women of the World includes pamphlets, circulars, and the executive minutes of the Associated Country Women of the World organization. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Virginia Association of Extension Home Economists consists of the history of home demonstrations, as well as both state and district reports from the National Home Demonstration Council. This series is organized chronologically.
Series V: National Virginia Family and Community Education includes yearbooks, correspondence, and other organizational material related to the organization. This series is arranged chronologically.
Series VI: Other Organizations contains material related to the VA Mother's Committee and the Virginia Cooperative Extension Civil Rights Compliance organization. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series VII consists of four subseries. Subseries A: Audio contains recording reels related to the Bicentennial Quilt Project. Subseries B: Photographs and Negatives includes photographs related to the Bicentennial Tapestry, as well as many unlabeled negatives. Subseries C: Slides consists of picture slides of organization activities, many of which document 4-H camps and projects. It also includes slides and presentation materials on such topics as "How to Give a Good Speech" and the "Growth and Development of Youth." Subseries D: VHS Tapes includes a variety of videos on such topics as "Puppy to Do Training," and "Self Esteem in School-Aged Children." Many of the VHS tapes relate to the 4-H program. All subseries are arranged chronologically.
Series VIII: Artifacts contains artifacts related to VEHC including 4-H award plaques, the NEHC seal, the Bedford Country 4-H Flag, a 50th anniversary commemorative plate and bell, and the Extension Homemakers Crest. The series is arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
National Extension Homemakers Council. Virginia Chapter. (U.S.); National Home Demonstration Council. Virginia Chapter. (U.S.); Virginia Cooperative Extension Service.
Subjects:
4-H clubs; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Virginia Cooperative Extension Service
Contents List
- Series I: National Extension Homemakers Council, 1957-1997
  - Song and 50th Anniversary, 1957, 1986 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - National Notes, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - "The Homemaker," 1977 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Newsletter of the NEHC (incomplete), 1982-1987 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Certified Volunteer Unit Program, 1983 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - "A Force for Families" NEHC Council Conference, 1986 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Newsletter of the NEHC,1988-1990 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Meeting Minutes (incomplete), 1988-1993 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Newsletter of the NEHC, 1991-1997 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Photograph Scrapbook of VPI Meeting, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
  - VPI Meeting, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)
- Series II: Virginia Extension Homemakers Council, 1948-2007
  - Subseries A: Administration and Organizational History
    - Law and Religious Concerns Compliance, 1948-1982 (Box-folder 6-6)
    - History, 1960-1999 (Box-folder 6-4)
    - Annual Reports, 1972 (Box-folder 2-6)
    - Inactive Clubs, 1972-1983 (Box-folder 17-19)
    - Financial Reports, 1972-1993 (Box-folder 5-6)
    - Annual Reports, 1973 (Box-folder 2-7)
    - Annual Reports, 1974 (Box-folder 2-8)
    - Annual Reports, 1975 (Box-folder 3-1)
    - VEHC Club Membership and Treasurer's Reports, 1975-1984 (Box-folder 17-26)
    - Annual Reports, 1976 (Box-folder 3-2)
    - Budget / Operating Funds, 1976-2000 (Box-folder 5-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1977 (Box-folder 3-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1978 (Box-folder 3-4)
    - Early History, 1979 (Box-folder 5-4)
    - Guidelines Compliance, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 5-7)
    - Annual Reports, 1979 (Box-folder 3-5)
    - Annual Reports, 1980 (Box-folder 3-6)
    - History, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 6-5)
    - Annual Reports, 1981 (Box-folder 4-1)
    - Annual Reports, 1982 (Box-folder 4-2)
    - Annual Reports, 1983 (Box-folder 4-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1984 (Box-folder 4-4)
    - Annual Reports, 1985 (Box-folder 4-5)
    - NEHC 50-Year Member Certificate Application, 1986-1990 (Box-folder 17-27)
    - Administrative Materials, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2-5)
    - Tax Status (IRS), 1990-1994 (Box-folder 7-4)
    - VEHC Member Enrollment Forms, 1991 (Box-folder 17-20)
    - VEHC Member Enrollment Forms and Mailing Lists, 1992 (Box-folder 17-21)
    - VEHC Member Enrollment Forms, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 17-22)
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1993-2000 (Box-folder 5-2)
    - Extension Homemakers Member Report, 1988, n.d. (Box-folder 17-28)
  - Subseries B: Programs and Projects
    - Heritage Project - Fluvanna, Greene, Cumberland and Louisa Counties, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 5-9)
    - Heritage Project - York, Gloucester, Charles, Hampton, Newport and Warwick Counties, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 6-3)
    - Heritage Project - Stafford, Spotsylvania, Westmoreland, Caroline, and King George Counties, 1967 (Box-folder 6-2)
    - Heritage Project - Louden, Page, and Warren Counties, 1967 (Box-folder 6-1)
    - Heritage Project - Augusta, Highland, Rockingham, Madison, and Prince William Counties, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 5-8)
    - Tapestry Project, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 7-3)
    - "Old Dominion Echoes," 1975-1993 (Box-folder 7-1)
    - Report on Virginia's Bicentennial Tapestry, 1977 (Box-folder 17-1)
    - Area Meeting Programs, 1982-1993 (Box-folder 4-6)
    - Extenstion Homemakers Study, 1984 (Box-folder 5-5)
    - 4-H Leader Orientation Training, 1984 (Box-folder 17-17)
    - Three 4-H New Leader Orientation Visual Aid Flip Charts, July 1984 (Box 21)
    - Area Programs, 1985 (Box-folder 5-1)
    - "Let's Start Eating Smart" Program, 1991 (Box-folder 6-7)
    - Children's Television Workshop Booklets, 1994 (Box-folder 17-29)
    - Bicentennial Tapestry Image CD-ROM, 2007 (Box-folder 17-3)
    - Bicentennial Tapestry Script & Documents CD-ROM, 2007 (Box-folder 17-4)
  - Subseries C: Scrapbooks and Memorabilia
    - Scrapbook, 1972 (Box 16)
    - Scrapbook - 50th Anniversary, 1986 (Box 16)
    - Scrapbook, 1988 (Box-folder 7-2)
- Series III: Associated Country Women of the World, 1989-1993
  - Pamphlets, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 7-7)
  - The Country Women's Council, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 8-2)
  - Executive Minutes, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 7-6)
  - Circulars, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 7-5)
  - "The Country Woman," 1991-1993 (Box-folder 8-1)
- Series IV: Virginia Association of Extension Home Economists, 1952-1971
  - National Home Demonstration Council State Reports, 1952-1955 (Box-folder 9-6)
  - National Home Demonstration Council State Reports, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 9-5)
  - VHDAA Notes, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 8-8)
  - VHDAA Reports, 1961 (Box-folder 8-10)
  - VHDAA Reports, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 8-11)
  - VHDAA Committee and District Reports, 1962 (Box-folder 8-5)
  - VHDAA Reports, 1963 (Box-folder 8-12)
  - Virginia Home Demonstration Agents Association Committee Reports, 1964 (Box-folder 8-4)
  - VHDAA Committee Reports, 1965 (Box-folder 8-6)
  - VHDAA Reports, 1966 (Box-folder 9-1)
  - VAEHE Reports, 1967 (Box-folder 9-2)
  - VAEHE Reports, 1969 (Box-folder 9-3)
  - VAEHE Notes, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 9-4)
  - Virginia Federation of Home Demonstration Clubs Annual Report, 1970 (Box-folder 8-3)
  - VFHDC Notes and Reports, 1971 (Box-folder 8-9)
  - History of Home Demonstrations, n.d. (Box-folder 8-7)
- Series V: National and Virginia Family and Community Education, 1989-2003
  - VAFCE Advisor, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 9-7)
  - VAFCE Scholarship and Cookbook Information, 1990-1998 (Box-folder 10-2)
  - VFHDC Scholarship Information, 1990-1999 (Box-folder 10-3)
  - NFCE and VAFCE Yearbooks, 1990-2002 (Box-folder 10-4)
  - VAFCE Insurance Coverage, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 10-1)
  - VAFCE Bulk Mailing Permits, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 9-8)
  - VAFCE Club President's Reports, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 17-23)
  - 1995 FCE Membership, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 17-24)
  - VAFCE Organizational Forms and Materials, 1995 (Box-folder 17-18)
  - NAFCE Membership Forms, 1996 (Box-folder 17-25)
  - VAFCE Certificates of Deposit, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 9-9)
  - NAFCE Correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box-folder 9-11)
  - VAFCE Conference, 1998-2003 (Box-folder 9-10)
- Series VI: Other Organizations, 1963-1982
  - VA Mother's Committee, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 10-5)
  - Virginia Cooperative Extension Civil Rights Compliance, 1979-1982 (Box-folder 10-6)
- Series VII: Multimedia, 1979-1996
  - Subseries A: Audio
    - "Bicentennial Quilt Audio Track Recording Reel, n.d. (Box 13)
    - Bicentennial Quilt Slide Show Reel, n.d. (Box 13)
    - Bicentennial Tapestry Script Reel, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Subseries B: Photographs and Negatives
    - Jane Janey Photographs, 1979 (Box-folder 11-3)
    - Negatives (7 folders), 1981-1986, n.d. (Box-folder 17-30 to 17-36)
    - Bicentennial Tapestry Photographs, n.d. (Box-folder 17-2)
    - "Tapestry" Photographs and Slides, n.d. (Box-folder 11-1)
  - Subseries C: Slides
    - County Beef Show, Roanoke Jr. Beef Show, and School Clubs, 1979 (Box-folder 17-5)
    - 4-H Camp, 1979 (Box-folder 17-6)
    - 4-H Camp, 1980 (Box-folder 17-7)
    - 4-H Camp, 1981 (Box-folder 17-8)
    - 4-H Camp, 1982 (Box-folder 17-9)
    - 4-H Camp, Fashion Revue, Share the Fun, and VCE Marketing Slides, 1983-1984; n.d. (Box-folder 17-10)
    - "A Pictoral Story of the National 4-H Congress," 1984 (Box 18)
    - "A Pictoral Story of the National 4-H Congress" Slide Presentation Script, 1984 (Box-folder 17-38)
    - 4-H Camp, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 17-11)
    - 4-H, 1984-1993, n.d. (Box 18)
    - 4-H Camp, 1986 (Box-folder 17-12)
    - Montvale Project Groups, State Congress District Meeting, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 17-13)
    - 4-H Camp, 1987 (Box-folder 17-14)
    - 4-H Camp, Otter River School Club, 1989 (Box-folder 17-15)
    - 4-H Camp, National Resource Program, 1991, n.d. (Box-folder 17-16)
    - 4-H Bicycle, n.d. (Box 18)
    - 4-H Program: Genetics of Coat Color of Horses, n.d. (Box-folder 17-37)
    - "Be a 4-H Volunteer," n.d. (Box 18)
    - "Be a 4-H Volunteer" Slide Presentation Materials, n.d. (Box-folder 17-39)
    - "Cathedral" Color Slides, n.d. (Box-folder 10-7)
    - "Celebrating 50," n.d. (Box-folder 10-8)
    - "Duplicate" Slides, n.d. (Box-folder 10-10)
    - Grouped Slides (no title), n.d. (Box-folder 10-9)
    - "Growth and Development of Youth," n.d. (Box 18)
    - "Growth and Development of Youth" Slide Presentation Materials, n.d. (Box-folder 17-41)
    - "Growth and Development of Youth" Slide Presentation Poster, n.d. (Box 21)
    - "How to Give a Good Speech" & "How to Give a Good Demonstration," n.d. (Box 18)
    - "How to Give a Good Speech" & "How to Give a Good Demonstration" Slide Presentation Materials, n.d. (Box-folder 17-40)
    - Ungrouped, Untitled Slides, n.d. (Box-folder 11-2)
    - VEHC Bicentennial Tapestry, n.d (Box 12)
  - Subseries D: VHS Tapes
    - "What's a 4-H Presentation Really Like?" - 1985 Winners - Audrey Owen, Bedford, 1985 (Box 19)
    - 4H Guide Dog, 1985-1986 (Box 19)
    - NEHC "Rich Lives," 1986 (Box 14)
    - "Membership," 1987 (Box 14)
    - "Self Esteem in School-Aged Children," 1988 (Box 19)
    - "Volunteering in a World Turned Upside Down," (Oklahoma), 9/8/1988 (Box 19)
    - "America's Youth: The Challenge and the Opportunity," 1989 (Box 19)
    - Bedford 4-H, 1989 (Box 19)
    - VEHC Winter Board, 1991 (Box 14)
    - 4-H Director's Update,September 1991 (Box 19)
    - VEHC "Dispatch," 1992 (Box 14)
    - VEHC Winter Board, 1993 (Box 14)
    - FCE Video, 1996 (Box 14)
    - (4-H), "Kingdom of Mocha" - "Return to the Kingdom of Mocha" - "Becoming a Family" - "Design for Liberty" - "A Special Friendship," n.d. (Box 19)
    - "4-H... More Than You Even Imagined," n.d. (Box 19)
    - 4-H Camp Counseling - Roles and Responsibilities - Cooperative Extension Service - The Ohio State University, n.d. (Box 19)
    - 4-H "Citizenship Washington Focus Program," n.d. (Box 19)
    - 4-H Environmental Alert, n.d. (Box 19)
    - 4-H Home Building Blocks, n.d. (Box 19)
    - 4-H Youth Voices and Action, n.d. (Box 19)
    - 4-H Volunteer Middle Management Video, n.d. (Box 19)
    - AIDS Community Education and Action, Va. Cooperative Extension Service, n.d. (Box 19)
    - "AKC and the Sport of Dog" - "To Work with the Forest" - "Rumble of Wheels (Clydesdales)," n.d. (Box 19)
    - Citizens Creating Action, n.d. (Box 19)
    - "Citizenship Washington Focus," Promotional Video, n.d. (Box 19)
    - The Leader in You - "Shall we Dance," n.d. (Box 19)
    - Puppy to Dog Training, n.d. (Box 19)
    - Stock Market - Comm. Mkt. Training, n.d. (Box 19)
    - USDA - New Leader Orientation - The Big Story - 4H Program Committees, n.d. (Box 19)
    - "Working Together for America's Youth," n.d. (Box 19)
    - "Working Together for America's Youth" - Glimpses of Success, n.d. (Box 19)
- Series VIII: Artifacts, 1952-1986
  - Bedford County National 4-H Farm and Home Electric Program Award Plaque, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Farm and Home Electric Program Award Plaque, 1953 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Farm and Home Electric Program Award Plaque, 1954 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Safety Program Award Plaque, 1955 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Electric Program Award Plaque, 1956 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Electric Program, 1957 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Safety Program Award Plaque, 1958 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Electric Program Award Plaque, 1959 (Box 20)
  - Green's Drug Store Outstanding Home Demonstration Club of the Year Award Plaque, 1962-1990 (Box 20)
  - Bedford County National 4-H Electric Program Award Plaque, 1966 (Box 20)
  - Whereabouts Club Outstanding Scrapbook Award Plaque, 1981-1982 (Box 20)
  - 50th Anniversary Commemorative Bell, 1986 (Box 15)
  - 50th Anniversary Commemorative Plate, 1986 (Box 15)
  - Whereabouts Club Scrapbook Contest Winner Award Plaque, 1986 (Box 20)
  - 4-H Bedford Flag, n.d. (Box 21)
  - Extension Homemakers Crest, n.d. (Folder 1)
  - NEHC Seal, n.d. (Box 15)
  - National Extension Homemakers Council Cooperative Extension Service Tile, n.d. (Box 20)